Welcome to our lecture on VLSI very large scale
integration. We're going to lay out some circuits
using basically a paint program to build millions
of transistors and use photo lithography. So when
I was in master's degree long time ago, I used a
tool called magic. This was an open-source VLSI
layout tool that was created at Berkeley in 1983
and it's very very popular because it's free. And
if you Google things like how to build a VLSI
NANDgate, you will see lots and lots of magic
demonstrations on YouTube. I decided not to have
you use magic. That's just a little too much.
It's really a powerful and sophisticated tool.
So, what I did was build little simple circuit
layout tools. So, all my tools are built for this
course. They're not real layout tools. You can't
really do layout with them. All I care about is
the learning objectives in this course. They run
in the browser, don't require any installation,
but don't push them too hard. If you build super
complex circuits that might be valid circuits, my
emulators will fall apart. Just do the homework in
them, play in them, have a good time, but don't
try to get too sophisticated. If you really
want to install more sophisticated emulators,
either, you know, on your computer or online,
well, you have fun with that. This is just to get
you started. So the first thing we're going to
talk about is how to map the VLSI COS knot. So we
have a KN gate, the abstraction zero goes to one,
one goes to zero. And we have a CMOS layout where
we have an a POS transistor at the top and a NOS
transistor at the bottom. We've gone through
that in some detail. And on the right is the
VLSI layout for that. So, let's talk a little
bit about what it takes to do VLSI layout. So,
the Mystic program that I wrote for you does
painting on a grid and you can paint various
things. You can paint multiple things in one
little grid cell. Like the blue, light blue
in this case going across the top is metal and the
pink is polyilicon and the green is endop silicon.
and the orange is p- dope silicon. And you lay
these out by simply drawing them. And you'll see
that there's also a voltage source on the metal
in the top example. Now, these are not necessarily
connected. They can pass by each other. And in
particular, metal passes by everything unless
you connect it. And you connect it by punching
a little hole in it using what's called a via.
And it's a vertical ne connector between the
layers. So you can see in the top diagram that
the polysilicon endop silicon and pope silicon
does not have any positive charge. That's because
they're not really connected to the metal. But if
you put vas at each of the connections then the
positive charge moves from the metal to the poly
polysilicon endop silicon and pdop silicon. Now to
make a transistor it takes polysilicon plus Ndoped
or P do silicon and you create the transistor
whether it's an NOS transistor or POS transistor.
When you cross polysilicon crosses Ndoped it makes
an NOS transistor and when a polysilicon crosses
posed it produces a POS transistor. So if we look
we see metal across the top. We see a vertical
ndoped and a vertical p-doped coming down with
a via. And then we have a horizontal polysilicon
with a plus charge on it. And at the moment that
it's crossing the green or the endoped, it causes
a transistor. And given that that is an NOS
transistor when positive voltage is transmitted to
through it then it copies the voltage through it.
The POS on the other hand when it's presented with
a one basically it blocks and so you can see the
positive voltage flowing down the POS but stopping
at the transistor. And so these overlaps between
the ndoped and p-oped and the polysilicon are the
transistors. And if you look at the bottom one,
you see the exact same circuit that has
a zero or negative on it. And you see
that the NOS transistor is blocking and the POS
transistor is conducting. Now the layout here,
my little layout is greatly simplified and my
circuit emulation is greatly simplified. It's
good enough to do not gates and nan gates and
NOR gates. And if you're really interested, you
can ask AI to explain the differences between VLSI
layout and uh actual manufacturing layout because
there's actual differences in the construction.
For example, you're you can draw it on my system,
but you you're not supposed to overlap N
and P uh dope silicon due to manufacturing,
limitation. But if you want to connect them, you
throw a little piece of metal in a couple levas
and then you can connect them. So, if you're using
the circuit simulation software, you can turn on
this layer mode where you point at a layer and it
shows the layers from top to bottom. And again,
this isn't perfectly right, but you can see
like on the left you can see a polysilicon
and a p-doped silicon and you see them connect and
that makes a poss transistor. You can see that on
the on the layer chart where the P and the poly
are touching and that's where the transistor is
being created. And then if you look on the right
where you have the metal and the pdoped silicon,
they are connected via a via. And you can think
of the via as a little hole that's drilled through
all the layers with a little kind of bit of metal
poured in. So they're all actually connected.
And so that via is how the metal the positive
charge goes from the metal at the top to the
pdoped silicon uh vertic going down vertically.
So here is a cos knot and you you can see that
it creates a pos transistor at the top and an
MOS transistor at the bottom. It uses metal to
move the the voltages around and V is to connect
the various silicon layers at the right point. And
so you see the input on the right on the left side
is a zero and then goes to the two transistors the
POS at the top and the N MOS at the bottom. And
you can see one of them in the case of the input
zero the NOS at the bottom is non-conducting and
so the ground is not going to output but the top
POS transistor is conducting. So the positive
is is then copied to the output just like in
the circuits we were looking at before. And if you
switch the input to one, then the POS transistor
at the top stops conducting and the NOS transistor
at the bottom starts conducting. And so the the
negative the ground that's coming up from the
bottom is conducted through the NMOS transistor
to the output. And so now we have a knot. And I
won't go through everything about this, but you
can then extend this to make things more complex
than not. And so we we talked a little bit about
nan gates. NAND gates have two POS transistors
at the top and two NOS transistors at the bottom.
It's kind of like a kind of half parallel half in
series not gate and and if you trace the little
picture you can see that I've I've created that
you can see there's four transistors and I will
do a demonstration where it actually reads the
whole circuit so you can watch it in slow motion.
But you can see the voltage at the top. That's the
voltage in the ground at the bottom. And you can
see the voltage coming down through some VAS to
some pdope silicon. You can see the two inputs.
And you can see them in this case they're both
one and they are in effect being transported.
You see a place where the the second input is
being connected to polysilicon. Then it's going
over top of a different polysilicon. Then it is
going on top of a p-doped silicon and then it is
connecting to a horizontal polysilicon so that it
can be make a transistor for the other of the POS
transistors that make the nan gate up. Now if we
look at the bottom the bottom is thing where we're
deciding whether negative is going out or not.
And in this case because they're both positive and
there's two NOS transistors you can see the the
green endope silicon going up. And because both
inputs are positive, both of those transistors
are transmitting. And so what's being copied
to output is the negative from ground. So if we
switch to a different row in the truth table, A
of zero and B of one, we can see how the nan gate
changes a little bit, right? So the zero goes and
makes it so that the P+ is conducting at the top.
That's conducting a plus down. Then that is going
to make the output be plus. And then you watch
that same ground, that same zero go down to the
top NOS transistor. And then that blocks that NOS
transistor that keeps ground from flowing out. And
so it's you can trace all of the traces and all
the connections and all the VAS and see there's
transistors and connections and they basically
implement the circuit diagram of the NAND.
This has been a long series of lectures talking
about semiconductors. We started about tubes
and how do tubes and transistors need to be
tuned for digital applications where they
have sort of the the the quick transition at
the 1/3 point for digital applications. Again,
these are analog devices although we want
to treat them and think of them as digital.
Then we go from transistors to gates which
makes it so that we can think digital even
though the underlying thing is uh an analog
transistor. Then we've watched the evolution
of transistor technology from POS to NOS and then
currently CMOS and how photoiththography makes it
so we can put more and more transistors
on the chip over time and manufacturing
has gotten better over time. And we did a
really brief introduction to how to design
VLSI design chips using VLSI layout tools. So
I hope you found that interesting. Up next,
we're going to switch from transistors to pure
digital logic and design much more sophisticated
circuits using exclusively digital logic
and gates. [Music] [Applause] [Music]